rics.org 2009-06-17

# Privacy policy

**RICS Privacy Policy  
** RICS (which means here the Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors and its associated companies) is committed to protecting your privacy and this Privacy Policy sets out our privacy practices. Please take the time to review this Privacy Policy carefully as it tells you how your personal information will be treated by us. 

By using any RICS website (our "Sites") and our services, you unconditionally agree to be bound by this Privacy Policy. Our Sites are located at: 

and such additional and replacement sites from time to time. 

RICS wants to offer you the best possible internet experience. Consequently additional functions, features, products or services are incorporated into Our Sites from time to time. 

This, and our commitment to protecting the privacy of your personal information, may result in periodic changes to this Privacy Policy. 

As a result, please remember to refer back to this Privacy Policy regularly to review any amendments. 

If we change our Privacy Policy we will post the changes on this page and may place notices on other pages of our Sites.

Any questions regarding our Privacy Policy should be directed to:

Legal Department   
RICS  
12 Great George Street  
Parliament Square  
London SW1P 3AD  
United Kingdom 

Alternatively see the section "Contacting Us" below.

**What do we collect and use personal information for?  
** In order to: 

  * **Control access to restricted member areas of our Sites;**
  * **Process orders or applications submitted by you;**
  * **Customise the service we provide to you;**
  * **Administrate your membership or otherwise carry out our obligations in relation to any agreement you have with us;    **
  * **Verify your identity (for example, in the event you are a member)    **
  * **Anticipate and resolve problems with any goods or services supplied to you;**
  * **Carry out market research and tracking of sales data;    **
  * **Provide you with necessary communications such as EGM notices;    **
  * **Send you news and information about events, publications and services;**
  * **Administer member professional conduct issues;**
  * **Monitor CPD compliance.**

We need to collect and process personal information about you including your name, gender, birth date and so forth. 

We may ask you for this information through our Sites, or via one of our service centre operators, or we may collect this information through your email or other communications with us. 

Certain information is collected automatically, as described later in this Privacy Policy.

Although we do not make it compulsory to give us every item of information we ask for, the more information you volunteer (and the more accurate it is), the better we can tailor our services for you.

We also collect information from you if you choose to take part in any of our surveys. We use this information to help us plan promotional campaigns.

Certain RICS services, such as the RICS Directory, are offered in conjunction with our business partners. 

In such cases, we may need to share your personal information with them in order to provide these services. 

Please note that certain services may be unavailable if you do not want to disclose the personal information you are asked for.

**Log files and IP addresses**  
When you visit our Sites, we automatically log your IP address (the unique address which identifies your computer on the internet) which is automatically recognised by our web server. We use IP addresses to help us administer our Sites and collect broad demographic information for aggregate use. 

Anonymous user data is collected on a monthly basis for us by WebtraffiQ ( **[www.webtraffiq.com](http://www.webtraffiq.com/)** )

**Non personal information  
** We may automatically collect non-personal information about you such as the type of internet browsers you may use or the site from which you linked to our Sites. 

You cannot be identified from this information and it is only used to assist us in providing an effective service from our Sites.

We may from time to time supply the owners or operators of third party sites from which it is possible to link to our Sites with information relating to the number of users linking to our Sites from their sites. 

You cannot be identified from this information.

**Information placed on your computer  
** We may store some information (commonly known as a "cookie") on your computer when you look at our Sites. 

This information facilitates your use of our Sites and helps us to provide you with the best level of service. 

For example, cookies ensure that you do not need to re-enter your details every time you order from us or visit our restricted member access site and help us to show you advertisements which are relevant to your interests.

You can erase or block cookies from your computer if you want to (your help screen or manual should tell you how to do this), but certain RICS services may not work correctly or at all if you set your browser not to accept cookies.

**Disclosing your information to others  
** Other than the disclosures referred to here, we will not disclose any personal information without your permission unless we are legally entitled or obliged to do so (for example, if required to do so by Court order or for the purposes of prevention of fraud or other crime).

**Information about products and services  
** It is very important to us that we provide the highest level of service. 

In order to help us do this, from time to time, RICS companies may send you details of products and services which we think may be of interest to you. 

In addition, from time to time, RICS companies may share the information you supply to us with selected third parties to enable them to send you information which may be of interest to you. 

Member data may also be used to provide mailing lists to selected and relevant third party suppliers for direct marketing. 

These member lists are selected on the basis of professional specialisation, location, company size etc. 

If at any time you do not wish to receive these details or us to share your information in this way, then please contact us at:

RICS Contact Centre  
Surveyor Court  
Westwood Way  
Coventry CV4 8JE  
United Kingdom  
T + 44 (0) 870 333 1600  
F +44 (0) 20 7334 3800  
E [contactrics@rics.org](mailto:contactrics@rics.org)

**Keeping our records accurate  
** We aim to keep our information about you as accurate as possible. If you would like to review or change the details you have supplied us with, you may do so at any time by contacting us directly or where this facility is offered through one of our Sites. If you have another query relating to your information please contact us as set out below.

**Discussion Boards  
** Our Sites make chat rooms, forums, message boards and/or news available to its users. Any information that is disclosed in these areas becomes public information and you should always be careful when deciding to disclose your personal information.

**Security  
** The internet is not a secure medium. We have implemented current secure technology and policies to help safeguard your privacy from unauthorised access and improper use and will continue to update these measures as new technology becomes available.

**Third party sites  
** We cannot be responsible for the privacy policies of other sites even if you access them using links from our Sites and recommend that you check the policy of each site you visit.

In addition if you linked to any of our Sites from a third party site, we cannot be responsible for the privacy policies and practices of the owners or operators of that third party site and recommend that you check the policy of that third party site and contact its owner or operator if you have any concerns or questions.

**Transferring your personal information outside the European Economic Area  
** As part of the services offered to you through our Sites, the information you provide to us may be transferred to countries outside of the European Economic Area ("EEA"). By way of example, this may happen if any of our servers are from time to time located in a country outside of the EEA or one of our service providers is located in a country outside of the EEA. 

We also share information between our National Associations, which are located in countries worldwide. These countries may not have similar data protection laws to the EEA. If we transfer your information outside of the EEA in this way, we will take steps to ensure that your privacy rights continue to be protected.

In addition, if you use our services while you are outside the EEA, your information may be transferred outside the EEA in order to provide you with those services.

**Contacting us  
** If at any time you would like to contact us with your views about our privacy practices, or with any enquiry relating to your personal information, you can do so by contacting us at:

RICS Contact Centre  
Surveyor Court  
Westwood Way  
Coventry CV4 8JE  
United Kingdom  
T + 44 (0) 870 333 1600  
F +44 (0) 20 7334 3800  
E [contactrics@rics.org](mailto:contactrics@rics.org)

You are entitled to ask for a copy of the information we store about you for which we charge you a small fee, currently £10.00.

**The Data Protection Commissioner  
** If you wish to know more about your rights in respect of protection of personal data, please contact: 

Data Protection Commissioner's Office  
Wycliffe House  
Water Lane  
Wilmslow  
Cheshire SK9 5AF  
United Kingdom  
T +44 (0)1625 545700  
 **[www.dataprotection.gov.uk](http://www.dataprotection.gov.uk/)**  and **[www.dpr.gov.uk](http://www.dpr.gov.uk/)**.
